Why is intense self-deception so important?
为什么高强度的自我欺骗很重要啊
Look at me, do I deceive myself?
你看我我欺骗
Do I usually deceive myself?
平时欺骗我自己吗
There are fewer scammers nowadays.
现在骗子少了
But I used to deceive a lot of people.
但我以前骗的人很多的
How can I put it?
因为怎么说
When we talk about a person's life
我们说一个人一生当中
and the many things they experience
经历的很多东西的时候啊
it largely depends on the path their parents set for them
取决于自己的父母给你安排了什么样的道路
You could say that the parents you were born to
可以说你抽中了的父母
have already determined most of your life circumstances
就已经抽中了你人生大部分的境遇
So why would you deceive yourself?
所以你为什么要自我欺骗
Deceiving yourself
自我欺骗
is about changing those foundational elements
就是在改变你之前设定的那些基础的那些啊
the basic settings of your life
元素基础的那些设定档
What was your original operating system like?
你原来的操作系统是什么样
Now, Brother Rong will give you a new one, right?
现在荣哥给你换一套吧对吧
I have always been that way.
我一直是一个啊
I wouldn't say I'm narcissistic.
非常非常非常都不能说是自恋吧
But I am in a state of brimming confidence. I've always believed I'm a chosen one. Why do I think I'm a chosen one? It's really interesting. Let me tell you why. Because there's no logic to it
但是来讲是一种自信满满的状态 就是我一直认为自己是天选之子 我为什么是天选之子呢 特别有意思啊 我跟你讲为什么啊 因为没有什么逻辑的事
It's just that my name, when broken down into strokes
就是我的名字把这个笔画拆解了以后呢
Happens to be six and one five
就正好是这个六和幺五
I was born on a stormy night
出生在一个呃暴风雨交加的一个夜晚
The day was calm and peaceful
那天白天的时候风平浪静的
But it was also overcast
但是又乌云密布
At exactly three o'clock in the morning
等我夜里三点整的时候
When I was born
生下来的时候
A bolt of lightning struck
咔嚓一道闪电啊
Then the rain started pouring down.
然后呢这个雨就下来了啊
Ever since then, I've been scared of gunshots,
然后我从此以后我就开始我就害怕什么枪声啊
fireworks sounds,
鞭炮声音啊
thunder,
打雷啊
I get really frightened.
我就特别害怕
Because I was startled right after I was born.
因为刚生下来被刺激了
You know?
你知道吗
It was exactly three o'clock,
就是三点整啊
when a baby boy was suddenly born at Peking Union Medical College Hospital.
突然在协和医院就降生了一个男婴啊
Then, after my forties, I look like this.
然后40多岁以后就是我这个样子
If you think there's anything suspicious about this,
要说这有什么奇怪的
it's not about what this object symbolizes as a good omen itself,
重要的不是这个东西本身是什么祥瑞之兆
that's not important. What matters is that I believe it to be a sign of good fortune. And after facing all sorts of dangers, years later, I found that this thing is truly real,
不重要啊 重要的是我认为他是一个祥瑞之照 而且在面临着各种各样的危险之后 多少年以后 我发现这个东西它是真的
it has become real.
它就变成真的了
Got it?
明白吗
The crucial part is when you start uncovering some secrets on your own.
重要的就是你自开始自己发现一些秘密的时候
You have to fool yourself a bit.
你就要骗自己
When you encounter some kind of divine hint or revelation,
你遇到什么样的天启的那种暗示了啊
or witness some miracle,
看到什么神迹了
or whatever it might be,
或者是怎么样来讲
you need to use these moments to motivate yourself.
你就要用这种方式来激励自己
To encourage yourself.
鼓励自己啊
This is really important.
这个东西很重要
The key is to convince yourself.
重要的是把你自己骗到了
When you truly believe you can do anything,
等你自己真认为自己能够啊上天入地
that you’re invincible,
无所不能
and then the spherical lightning appears,
放着球状闪电就出来了以后
at that point, you are in an unbeatable state.
你这个时候你现在这个状态是无敌的
That’s why those with NPD, the narcissists, are so powerful.
所以为什么那些NPD自恋狂特别的强呢
Sometimes they eliminate others through their strength,
有的时候他是通过实力来排除别人的
but more often, they overwhelm others with their presence.
有更多的时候他是用气势去压倒别人的
So this is crucial.
所以这个东西很重要
No matter what
无论怎么样
if you look at my life as a whole
你如果去看我的一生来讲话
you wouldn't think it was particularly successful or someone with a distinguished reputation you wouldn't think so but I've lived a carefree life very fulfilling, right? if something wasn't done
你都不会觉得这是一个啊非常成功的特别啊 名声卓著的这么一个人 你都不会这么想 但是这一生过得很潇洒 很痛快是吧 这个东西就是没做
there's nothing that can be done about it
那就没有办法
It's because my parents have always had my back that I've been able to live such a carefree and adventurous life.
就是为什么这一生会过得很痛快很潇洒
My parents have provided me with a lot of support, understanding, and help.
是因为父母给我兜底了啊
So I think, if this person...
父母给了我非常多的帮助和理解和支持
If the idea that good deeds from our ancestors really do have an impact...
所以我觉得如果这个人
If we believe that the good karma from our ancestors is real...
事实之间的这个命令是真知存在的话啊
I feel like I was born into this world to enjoy it, to play.
如果咱们说祖上积德是真实存在的话
To truly experience life in all its facets.
我这一辈子来这个人间感觉就是来玩儿的啊
But I have some friends...
来体验人生的真的是体验
But I have some friends
但是我有些朋友啊
Like other UPloaders
像其他的up主啊
I recently got to know two UPloaders
我最近认识了两名up主
one is a Shanghai migrant
一个是在上海的一个沪漂
and the other is a Beijing migrant
一个是在北京的一个北漂啊
both of them are truly remarkable
他们两个都非常的了不起啊
having left their home provinces after the college entrance exam
呃离开了高考大省
to study in Beijing
然后考到了北京
and to study in Shanghai
考到了上海
and after years of arduous effort
然后经过多少年的艰苦卓绝的努力
Parents still have NPD
父母还是NPD啊
it's still quite terrifying and in the marriage, one person isn't understood by the other and the one not in the marriage is relying on their cat for companionship and the fate, well, you can imagine how dire it is
还是非常可怕 然后呢自己在婚姻当中的这一位呢 又不被另一位理解啊 呃不在婚姻当中那一位呢 就是跟自己的猫相依为命啊 然后呃命运你听得多惨有多惨啊
it's not just about seeing your fate clearly
那根本不是说就是说你要把这个命运看清
or anything like that
或者怎么样
Or put it another way, change the mindset
或者说换了一个思想
Change the approach
换了一个手法
If I were to face those hardships
我要遇上他的那些苦难
I would be doomed
我一定完蛋
You know that, right?
你知道吗
Definitely doomed
一定会完蛋
But that's how it is
但就是这样来讲
If you want to maximize his transformation
你要对他进行最大化改造的话
You have to believe in yourself
你就一定要相信自己
Because of these things
因为这些东西
These kids from well-off families are usually very confident in themselves
这些家境好的孩子通常都是非常相信自己的
You just can't afford to have any more debuffs in your life
你就是不能在你的人生再出现各种DEBUFF了
To be honest
所以说实在的
Compared to these two friends of mine
我跟我这两个朋友相比
My life has been incredibly fortunate
是这我的人生是非常非常之幸运啊
Just how fortunate, you ask?
到幸运到什么程度啊
Let me tell you
我就跟你跟你说
I spent four years in junior high school
我初中念了4年
I took a year off in my third year of junior high.
我初三休了一年
I attended school for two semesters in my third year of junior high.
初三上了两个学期
I went for about two months.
上了两个月
Then I had a really bad allergic reaction.
然后就过敏的特别厉害
So I decided to take a leave from school.
然后我就休学了
But the real reason wasn't the allergy.
但其实真正的原因不是因为过敏
The actual reason was that I made a friend back then.
真正原因是我那时候交了个朋友啊
A buddy of mine and I were pretty close. He’s now a Taoist priest. Back then, we got really hooked on an online game called Ultima Online It was particularly famous even earlier than games like Three Kingdoms or the Jin Yong Heroic Legends
我一哥们跟我挺好的 他现在是个道士 我们那个时候呢迷上了一个网络游戏 叫做网络创世纪啊 优特别有名啊 就是比那个网络三国什么金庸群侠传还要早
earlier than EverQuest
比那个EVERQUEST啊
even earlier than EverQuest, a graphical online game
EEVEQ还要还要早的一个图形化网络游戏
It was 1997 back then
那个时候是1997年
I had just gotten on the internet
那个时候我刚上了因特网啊
I started playing this game in 1998
98年开始玩这个游戏啊
There was a server called Jeris Word in Shenzhen.
就在深圳的一个服务器叫jeris word
They were all private servers.
那都是私服啊
Back then, we used to play on these kinds of servers.
那时候玩的这种服务器
On average, there were about two to three hundred people online.
然后平均在线两三百人
It was a pretty simple online game, right?
就是很简单的一个这个网络游戏是吧
I was really hooked back then.
那时候沉迷了啊
But at that time, I was still using dial-up internet.
但是那个时候我还是拨号上网
My mom would apply for a dedicated phone line for me every month.
我妈每个月给我专门申请一条电话线
And I paid around seven to eight hundred yuan.
然后还交了七八百块钱啊
The phone bill in the early 90s was around seven or eight hundred yuan.
九几年的七八百块钱的这个电话费
They encouraged me to go online.
去这个指鼓励我上网
This was the phone bill.
这是电话费
In addition to the phone bill, there was also the internet fee.
电话费之外还有网费
So these were two separate expenses.
所以这是两笔钱
It was really, really tough.
非常非常不容易
But my parents were so indulgent with me.
但我父母就是这么的溺爱我
I had no choice.
我就没有办法啊
Actually, I did pretty well in junior high school. How good was I at studying in junior high? Not the kind that's associated with kids from Beijing, you know. Not the kind of good that comes from low difficulty studies. But the kind of good that's genuinely excellent. Just how good was I at studying?
这个我初中其实学艺是很好的 我初中学习好到什么程度啊 不是所谓的那种北京孩子的那种啊 学习难度低那种好 是那种真的学习非常好 学习好到什么程度呢
Let me tell you, the test papers from Haidian District were tough.
反而海淀区的卷子我就这么跟你说吧
When I was in eighth grade, I scored full marks in four subjects.
我初二的时候大概是四科是满分
One subject was 99 points.
有一科是99啊
And I can't remember what I scored in the last one.
就是还有一科忘了是多少分
It's probably 94.
好像94吧
Like my Chinese and English.
就是我的语文英语啊
Anyway, my physics and chemistry.
反正我的物理化学
Mathematics.
数学啊
English, all were full marks.
英语啊全是满分啊
Of course, we're talking about junior high school here.
就是当然来讲你说啊这是初中
But senior high school is much harder.
但高中难度高啊
But if you can get full marks in every subject in junior high, you're a prodigy.
但是初中你能科科拿满分已经是神童了
That's how good my academic performance was.
属于啊学习成绩就好到这个程度
So later on, I kept thinking about that class in the third year of junior high.
所以我后来呃我一直念念那个初三那个班
That teacher.
那个老师
He was quite strict, right?
他比较严格是吧
The teacher was quite strict.
那个老师比较严格
He basically supervised both the morning and evening self-study sessions.
他基本上就是早自习晚自习都有
He trained us, a group of Beijing kids, following the model of Hengshui High School.
他就按衡中那个模式就去练我们这帮北京孩子
So, to talk about it,
然后所以来讲的话
And regarding our school,
而且我们那个学校来讲
It had an experimental class.
他有实验班
But the teachers assigned to the experimental class are all excellent teachers. You know, our English teacher used to be... He would be in his late teens now. He should be over 120 years old by now. Just like back then.
但实验班配置的那个教师都是非常好的教师 你知道你像我们英文老师是原来在啊 他是现在的话活十多岁 都应该120多岁了那种 就是就是当年的那种
He's one of those early English students educated in a church school.
就是教会学校教出来的那种英文生
Do you know?
你知道吗
Those early English students had it particularly tough.
就是特别早那种英文生特别的不容易啊
I think that's a point worth noting.
我觉得这一点来讲
The faculty at the school
学校的师资
is really top-notch
师资那个呃师资配的是非常非常好的
but back then, all I wanted to do was play games
但是我当时就是想打游戏啊
because playing games online was so addictive
因为互联网上这个玩游戏非常的过瘾啊
I just loved playing games
就喜欢打游戏
I’d grab a computer
拿一个电脑
back then we even had Windows 98
那时候还有win98呢
and with Internet Explorer 4.0, I’d go online to play games
咳咳IE4.0就上网打游戏啊
ah, at first, I was actually quite into Mart
啊我最开始还我还其实我之前还迷过mart
So, I used to play with that z mart
就z mart用那个z mart玩
That mart is basically a word game
那mart就是文字游戏
To be honest, I started playing games very early
所以说实在的我玩游戏这个玩的非常早
I really enjoyed playing games
特别喜欢玩游戏啊
I was pretty much obsessed with games
沉迷于游戏
If it were other parents
如果这是别的家长的话
They might have sent me to Yang Yongxin
说不定就给我送杨永信那去了
To become one of those internet addicts
就成了这个战网魔
Right?
对不对
That, that fighting against internet addiction
那个那个对抗这个网络上瘾的
Turned me into a typical internet-addicted teenager But my parents didn’t My parents saw that I didn’t want to go to school back then Oh Playing games every day And not even sleeping Just neglecting meals and sleep to play
这么一个网瘾少年了 但是我爸我妈没有 我爸我妈看我那时候呢也不想上学 哎 天天玩游戏 然后呢也不睡觉啊 就那废寝忘食的玩
They never hit me
既没有打我
He didn't scold me either.
也没有骂我啊
He didn't do anything drastic.
也没有怎么怎么着
I just felt that not going to school...
就觉得那不上学
So, I decided not to go to school.
那就不上学吧
Right?
对不对
This is the age of computers now.
那个现在这个计算机的时代也来了
I let the kid focus on playing at home.
就让孩子在家专心玩啊
It's fine to learn some coding too.
没事再看看编程就挺好的
So I eventually took a leave of absence.
所以我后来我就办休学了
Yeah, I wasn’t feeling well either.
哎确实自己也不舒服
So I took a leave of absence from school.
就直接休学了
After taking a leave,
休学了以后
to be honest, that year,
然后那一年说实在的
I hung out with my buddy,
我就跟我这小哥们一块
No worries.
没事
We just played games,
我们就打游戏
and gamed together using QQ,
然后开黑用QQ
which is why my QQ number is pretty old.
所以我QQ号特别早嘛
The seven-digit number
呃七位的号嘛
So that was the year I really had a blast.
所以就是那个时候那一年给我玩爽了
We had a great time later on.
后来玩爽了
After this year is over
这一年玩完了以后
That game later became outdated.
这个游戏后来那个也就过气了
Then in the second year, I focused on my studies.
然后第2年就踏踏实实上学
Of course, the academic performance has declined.
当然学习成绩有所下降
He was supposed to be able to attend Renmin University High School.
本来应该是能上人大附中的
If I keep up my grades
我的成绩如果要是一直念下来
I should be able to attend Renda High School
应该能念人大附中
Actually, Brother Rong could possibly get into Tsinghua University Haha, just joking with you guys If I had gone to high school at Renda It would have been quite possible At least 101 Middle School would have been a possibility But later, it turned out to be the level of Jiaotong or Beihang University
就是其实荣哥是有可能能念清华的 哈哈就是跟你们开玩笑 如果要是我高中念了人 大部有可能啊 起码101也是有可能的 但是后来就就是交大北航这水平了
So, it ended up being one of the second-tier schools in Haidian District
所以就是海淀区的这第二梯队的学校啊
Of course, my grades were pretty impressive back then.
当然来讲我当时成绩确实很厉害啊
Even the finance school in Haidian reached out to me.
因为海淀金融学校还找过我
I attended some specialized classes for math and physics.
上过什么数学和物理的特长班
But I didn’t think I had the aptitude for science.
但是我认为我没有理科的功夫
I could still get full marks in middle school.
初中的东西还能拿满分
But that was all over in high school.
高中就没戏了啊
Because my mind was no longer on studying.
啊因为我的心思已经不在学习上了
It was all about gaming and chasing girls.
已经在游戏跟泡妞上边了啊
Yeah.
已经呃
I roughly know the story about meeting that beautiful senior when I was 14.
大概知道我14岁遇到那个漂亮学姐的故事啊
Even now, her beauty still outshines everyone else's.
现在看学姐的颜值也是秒杀一切的啊
Pretty much, she was unbeatable.
基本上来讲都是无敌的呃
So, I was quite smitten.
所以我心分的比较厉害
My heart was initially set on girls.
我的心最开始就在女人身上了
But it was already focused on games.
就已经在游戏身上了
So, back then,
所以那个时候来讲
I believed life should aim high.
我认为人生志在高远
Haha, it had nothing to do with the college entrance exam.
哈哈跟高考没什么关系啊
Of course, I ended up paying a heavy price for it later.
然后呢当然我后来也因为这个吃了很大的亏
I took a lot of detours.
走了很大的弯路啊
But it's not a big deal.
也没有什么关系
However, I always believe that life’s circumstances and such, Money comes and goes, but it will come back. Fate ultimately has a plan for us. As long as we don’t break the law,
但是我一直认为人生的这个境遇之类的 千金散尽还复来啊 命运是最终会有一对我们有安排的 只要不犯法啊
As long as we don’t have kids too early,
只要不提前生孩子
As long as we don’t do things that go against the natural order.
只要不干这些太那个这个违背这个规律的事啊
Let's just speak normally here.
只要正正常常来讲
Whether you're in school or not,
不管你是上学也好
or have left school,
离开学校也好的话
you can still achieve something significant,
都是有一番作为
you can still carve out a place for yourself.
有一番天地的啊
But life doesn't work on assumptions.
但是人生不能假设啊
But what I want to tell you is,
但是我就是想跟你们说的是
even if my grades dropped,
就是我父母即使就是学习成绩下降
I was still obsessed with games.
贪玩儿游戏
Then not going to school
然后不去上学
Speaking of this attitude of disliking school
这种厌学的这种态度来讲的话
I didn't feel there was anything wrong with me
也没觉得我是有毛病啊
I didn't think there was any psychological issue
也没觉得我是心理出现什么问题
He didn't hit me
也没打我
He didn't scold me
也没骂我
He didn't smash my computer
也没有砸我的电脑
I did smash my computer in the early days
我前期倒砸过我电脑
But it was because I didn't get his call
但是就是因为没接到他电话
You know,
你知道吧
because he didn't answer his call while riding the electric scooter.
因为骑电动车没接到他电话啊
Let's not get into that.
这就不说了
Another story is that my parents didn't smash my computer,
另外一个故事就是我爸妈也没砸我电脑
and they kept paying the internet bills for me.
也一直给我吭哧吭哧交着网费
Think about it, in the 90s,
你想90年代啊
paying a few hundred dollars for the phone bill, and even getting a dedicated phone line for the internet fee, so I could go online. It was back in '97. You can imagine how early that was. Right? So, my mom has always been supportive of me learning computer skills,
交个几百块钱的电话费 网费专门给我申请一条电话线 让我能够上网 就是97年啊 你想那是很早了啊 对不对 所以来讲我妈一直对我学计算机啊
and studying English and getting online.
学英文上网这些事儿都是比较支持的
My dad also believed these things should be left to the child's own development.
我爸也是觉得这些事情应该任由孩子自己发展
It turns out their choices were right.
事实证明他们这么选择是对的
Because I ended up excelling in these areas.
因为我最终就是这几项强嘛
Right?
对不对啊
These are the strong points.
就是这几项比较强
However,
但是来讲的话
if you compare yourself to the real programming geniuses,
你要跟那些真正的编程天才比
you can't compete.
没有办法比
But I was never a genius anyway,
但我本来就不是天才
so I shouldn't be trying to take the genius route, huh?
我就不应该走天才之路哈
If I had always been learning like a teacher,
如果我学习一直是像老师似的
I wouldn't play games,
我不玩游戏呃
I wouldn't chase girls
我不泡妞
Not having a girlfriend or anything like that
不交女朋友之类的
Always focusing on my studies
一直好好学习
Always doing that sort of thing
一直那什么
In the end, I got a big scholarship
最后考了个大富
I might end up getting into Tsinghua University
我可能最后能上清华
Or I might not get into Tsinghua University
可能最后上不了清华
At least get into a 985 university
上个985
At least get into a 211 university
上个211
But I won't be happy my whole life
但我这一辈子不会快乐的
I didn’t get to have fun during the time when I should have been playing.
我在最该玩儿的年纪没有玩儿
I wouldn’t be happy.
我就不会快乐
You know that, right?
知道吧
So, when I talk about it,
所以来讲的话
a lot of people say,
很多人就说啊
Bro Rong,
荣哥
what you have,
你这个东西
we really envy you.
你这个我们很羡慕你
Or, you’re just following the Beijing kids’ playbook.
或者你这就是北京孩子那套的套路
That's right.
是是这样没错
However, to put it another way, it's not that more children in Beijing have taken advantage of the excellent learning environment around them. Did he go to a good school? I, on the other hand, didn't have such opportunities. And I didn't work hard either.
但是来讲的话 不是有更多的北京孩子才利用了 这么身边很好的学习环境 他上了很好的学校吗 我就属于那种呃没有遇上这样的机会 我也没有努力
So I don't deserve these things.
所以我就不该得到这些东西啊
So I don't feel bad about not attending Tsinghua University.
所以我也没有觉得不上清华
It's not like the world ends if you don't go to Peking University.
不上北大就怎么着的一件事啊
I don't think I have that talent either.
我也不认为我自己有那个才能
At least, I didn't have that perseverance.
起码没有那个毅力啊
So, as you can see, I only attended school for a month in my entire life.
所以你看我后来这辈子就上过一个月啊
And worked for two weeks.
两个星期的班嘛
So things have always been that way.
所以一直也是这样
I think human potential can be channeled into various fields.
所以我觉得人类的那个能量
It doesn't have to be confined to formal education and employment.
它是会用在各个不同的领域的
There are many different paths one can take.
不一定非得是上学上班走正常的路啊
I can only say getting married and having kids
只能说娶妻生子
then going on blind dates
然后去相亲
following the normal path
去那什么走正常的道路
he will definitely be a certain way
他就一定是怎么样
if you find it suddenly interesting
你如果觉得突然有意思的话
then you could take a gap year
那你就gap year1年
of course
当然来讲
let me tell you
我跟你说
given your family circumstances
在你的家庭条件下
Maybe there are so many now
可能现在这么多
It might seem unrealistic when you're young
你在你年轻的时候不现实
But as you grow up
但是你长大了以后
If you can do it this way
你这么着能这么干的话
Just do it once
就干一次啊
Of course, everyone's willingness to take risks varies
当然每个人的能冒险的程度不一样
But when I talk to everyone
但是我就跟大家说的时候
I mean, when you fall into a set routine
就是说当你落入了既定轨道
Like my two UPloader friends Becoming a wife Becoming a mother Or becoming what your parents envisioned for you This is typically the state of most people in their twenties and thirties
就跟我这两个up主朋友似的啊 成为人妻 成为孩子的妈妈啊 或者说成为了一种父母预想到的你的状态时候 这个时候是人大多数二三十岁的状态
When you are in your twenties and thirties
就是你二三十岁的时候
You are often shaped by others into a husband
实际上你会被别人塑形成丈夫啊
A father
父亲啊
A son
儿子啊
This employee, a graduate
这个职员毕业生
It means that by the time you're 40, you realize
就是说你这一辈子到40岁的时候
your life is truly starting over for the second time.
你的人生你才意识到了真正的二次的开始
As Jung said,
就是荣格说的
the second beginning of life is when you start living for yourself.
人生的二次开始就是你为自己而活了
You shed the expectations others have for you,
你抛去了这些别人他人的对你的憧憬
the roles they set for you.
他人对你的设定
That's why I often say, social conditioning
所以我常说一句话叫社会化规劝嘛
is like society hoping you'll be a cog in the machine,
就是社会希望你做一个啊螺丝钉
hoping you'll be a certain way.
希望你做一个怎么样
What about someone with a discerning heart?
似有心人怎么样
Of course, having a new person involved is right.
当然来讲似有新人是对的
But, the true value of your life
但是来讲你的人生的真正价值
Who are you really?
你到底是谁
This is something you need to explore.
这个东西你需要去探索的啊
It's a process of exploration.
这是探索的过程
I feel like my entire life has been about taking a break from school since my teenage years.
我觉得我整个的人生都从十几岁开始休学开始
During that time, I truly lived for myself.
我那段时间是真正为我自己而活的
Because during that period, all I wanted to do was play games. Back then, I only wanted to have online relationships. I just wanted to play video games. At 14, I could get away with that. That was because I had parents who could support me. My parents didn’t have high expectations for my future.
因为那段时间我只想打游戏啊 那段时间我只想网恋 只想打游戏 14岁的我我就能这么干 是因为我有能托底的父母 我父母也没觉得我将来怎么着
They thought if I could go to college, I would.
我父母觉得我将来能上大学就上大学
If not, they were fine with that too.
上不了大学就不上大学
Right?
对不对
In the end, I did take a year off during college.
最终来讲我大学啊也是修了一次学
Why is that?
为什么呢
Because I found the major I was studying really painful.
因为觉得读的那个专业非常的痛苦
And the university wasn't great either.
那个学校也不好
Uh, cough cough
呃咳咳咳
I've always wanted to study art.
我又一直是想学艺术的
But I didn't get to study art.
没学成艺术
So I felt really frustrated.
我就特别的糟心
I felt really upset.
我就特别的难受
That's why I often skipped classes.
所以老不去上课
He kept skipping classes
老不去上课
and in the end, he went out to learn acting
最后呢又出去外边去学了表演了啊
so his mindset changed
所以那个心思就变了啊
I was determined to study film
我一定要学电影
I had to make it happen
我一定要怎么怎么着
and eventually, he went
后来就去了啊
to study film
学电影去了啊
starting from scratch to study film
重新另起炉灶学电影
but he ultimately completed his studies
但是最终也学完了啊
Ultimately,
最终来讲的话
life took some detours,
人生走了弯路
I repeated a year in middle school,
初中多念了一年
and I essentially repeated college,
大学等于多念了一次
actually more than once,
其实还不止一次
I went to college three times,
一共念了三次大学啊
across four different schools,
是四个学校
but three stints in college,
但是三次大学
so in total,
所以总总体来讲的话
There’s nothing in this life worth imitating.
这个人生没有什么可模仿的东西
But I’m very happy.
但是我过得很快乐
I’m incredibly happy. Because I’ve never lived a day not for myself. When I wanted to play games, that game was only popular for a while. I played it.
我过得特别快乐 因为我没有一天不是在为自己而活的 我想打游戏的年纪 那个时候那个游戏也就流行了那么一阵 我打了
When I was in college and should have been dating,
我在大学的时候该泡妞
I did, right?
我泡了对吧
It’s time to switch majors
该转专业
I did
我转了
It’s time to study abroad
该留学
I went abroad
我留了啊
So there’s nothing to regret in life
所以人生没有什么遗憾
It’s not like you have to get married in your teens
不是说你十几岁啊
Or even go to college
就就应该结婚啊
Or finish college and immediately start looking for a job
就应该甚至念大学
You should go out and look for a job right after finishing university.
就应该念完大学就出去找工作
It just turned out that way
就怎么怎么样
My life isn’t about what it should be
我的人生没有说应该怎么样
or what others are doing
或者别人怎么样
or what everyone else is up to
或者大家都怎么样
So, did it turn out that way?
然后就怎么样了没有
My parents have always created a laid-back lifestyle for me
我爸妈一直给我创造了一种随性的生活
Didn’t you not want to study that in college?
你不是大学不想念这个吗
Then you can switch to something else
那你就换一个
And just retake the college entrance exam
就这样重新高考
Still going out to study
还是出去读书
It's your choice
由你自己选择
I chose to study French
我选择的是学法语嘛
Then I went abroad to start over
然后出去外国去重新念了
Basically, I started from the first year again
等于是重新从大一开始念
That's how it is
就是这样
So you dislike Computer Science and Technology
那你不喜欢计算机科学与技术
There's nothing we can do about it
那没有办法
Right?
对不对
Even though you've been learning computer science since you were young
虽然你从小就学计算机
Even though we've spent so much money on your computer education
虽然给你花了那么多钱让你学计算机
But you found out that you're not cut out to be a programmer
但是你发现你自己不是程序员的料
Then you should have just given up and moved on Where does my interest lie? My interest lies in writing screenplays My interest is in acting I even got into filmmaking But the most interesting thing is that I ended up making films Acting can still bring in some money.
那你就果断放弃就完了啊 我的兴趣都在哪呢 我兴趣在写剧本上 我兴趣在做演员上 我甚至在拍片儿什么 可是后来最有意思的就是我后来拍片儿啊 当演员来讲还是能赚到一点钱
But the film production hasn't been particularly smooth.
拍片来讲的话一直不是特别顺利
So after many years,
所以后来经过多少年以后
I often ended up losing a lot of money on films.
我拍片经常赔了多少钱
If you add up all the film projects I've done,
我加一块拍片来讲的话
You'll see,
赔了你看啊
I've lost over 1.3 million.
赔了130多万得有了
Right?
对不对
Isn't that about the same as what I earned as a writer?
把我当写手那段钱花的不差不多了吗
This time I made my first pot of gold.
这一次赚了第一桶金
And I spent a quarter of it right away.
那花掉了直接就花掉了1/4啊
Of course, when you earn your own money, you spend it yourself.
当然自己挣钱自己花
That's quite normal.
这也很正常
But we all know that life has a margin for error.
但是我们都说人生的容错几率他是有的
You won't learn without hitting a few walls.
你不经过几次碰壁
You won't figure it out without taking a few gap years.
你不经过几个gap year
You won't find what you truly want to do.
不找到自己真正想的干的东西
You won't know what you're passionate about.
热爱的东西你是不知道的
I later realized that my production skills were lacking.
我实际后来就觉得我的制作的
My ability to shoot videos was quite poor.
拍片的能力很差啊
This was because my spatial imagination wasn't strong enough.
因为我的空间想象能力不够
My art foundation was also weak.
我的美术基础很差
But when it comes to understanding interpersonal dynamics,
但是我对于人与人之间这些东西呢
I have a better grasp of those aspects.
理解的比较多一点
So, my acting skills are relatively better. However, in terms of this aspect, it ultimately depends on what you're meant to do. what you'll ultimately be able to do what you'll ultimately contribute to society is something you can't predict I was in my thirties and still didn't know
所以我演技相对是好一点的 但是这个东西来讲 跟你最终该干什么 跟你最终能干什么 跟你最终会在为这社会贡献什么 你是不知道的 我30多岁那会儿还是不知道啊
so in the early stages, I seemed a bit aimless
所以我我前期看着我就比较比较那什么
you're already this old
你都这么大岁数了
how come you still haven't figured out what you want to do
你怎么还没想清楚你到底要干什么
spending your days fiddling with this and that
你这整天这东东捣鼓一下
how can that be okay
西捣鼓一下怎么行呢
The most important reason is this.
啊最重要的原因就是这样
A doting mother often spoils her child.
就是慈母多败儿啊
But from this perspective,
但是你从这个角度来讲哈
if you analyze it from the viewpoint of a normal person,
你从你们正常人的角度来讲分析
my parents,
就是我爸妈啊
having a son like me,
有我家儿子
consider themselves quite unlucky.
那算倒了霉了
However, in reality,
但是实际来讲
my parents have never thought much of me.
我爸妈从来没觉得我怎么样
Because from their perspective, I'm not an unsuccessful son
因为我没有他们从他们的眼里来讲的话
I'm exploring my own path
我并不是一个不出息的儿子
I'm taking a different route from others
而是我在探索自己的路
And this path might take a bit longer
我在走一条跟别人不一样的路啊
Even if you study until you're in your late twenties
而这条路可能会时间比较长啊
We support you
你就算读了大九大十
You can study as long as you want
我们也支持你
As long as there's food on the table at home
你想念书念到什么时候就念到什么时候
As long as there's something to eat at home
家里只要有一口吃的
As long as I don’t starve, nothing else really matters, right?
只要饿不死就没有什么关系对吧
Even if my parents are gone, I still need a place to live.
爸妈死了还要房子呢
When it comes to these things,
这些东西来讲的话
My parents have always been there to support me. So the ultimate point I’m trying to make is, The goal of today’s episode isn’t to brag to you all. What kind of life do you want to lead? How tough is your life right now? What’s the plan?
我爸妈一直在给我兜底 所以我最终说的这个目的 今天这一期的目的不是跟你们炫耀了 要做什么样的啊 要就你的人生现在有多惨 怎么样
You can't compare with me
没法跟我比
That's not the case
不是这样
I'm just saying, if you manage to stay in Beijing or Shanghai through hard work
我就是说如果你通过奋斗呆在了北京上海
then you're a medical representative
那你是一个学医代
you've made money
你有钱了
what will the future be like
将来怎么样了
if you can provide a great environment for your child
如果你能给你孩子提供很好的环境
I suggest that your child is worth raising
我建议你孩子是养不废的
you should follow the method they prefer
你就是按照他自己想的这种方法
Let him live his life.
让他去生活
Free-range parenting might actually be better.
放养其实有可能更好
Or if your child's personality is similar to mine,
或者说如果你的孩子性格跟我差不多
raising them this way will definitely be fine.
你就这么养它绝对没有问题的
Because a prodigal's return is invaluable.
因为浪子回头
In the end, he will find his place.
金不换这东西
All the hardships he endures will eventually pay off.
他最终会找到自己的位置的
The detours he takes will ultimately lead him to where he needs to be.
他最终一切吃的苦都会有回报的那一天
Those winding paths he walks
他最终走过的那些弯路
What seemed like a detour at the time
现当初看起来是弯路
What seemed like a detour in society
社会上看起来是弯路
What seemed like neglecting one's duties
是不务正业
But in life, there's nothing that shouldn't be explored
但是人生没有什么不该探索的地方
Can you say that what you explored was wrong?
你能说你探索的东西是有错的吗
So what was your purpose in playing The Elder Scrolls?
那你说你玩上古卷轴的目的是什么
You went straight to every quest marker
每个地方你都直接进入任务任务标识
Then you finished the main storyline and that was it? No, you had to explore every cave Every skill has been explored. Every place has been thoroughly scavenged. This is what makes life enjoyable.
然后把主线打完了就完了吗 不是你要把每一个洞穴都探索了 每一个技能都探索了 每一个地方收集的能收集的都收集完了 这才是人生人生才有乐趣
You've taken down all five guilds.
你把五大公会都打完了
You've defeated the Dark Brotherhood.
把黑暗兄弟会打了
You've taken out the Fighters Guild.
把这个战士公会打了
The Mages Guild has been defeated.
魔法师公会打了
The Thieves Guild has been taken care of, right?
盗贼公会打了对吧
Then you've taken down the Blades.
再把刀锋战士打了
There's a lot of stuff
就很多东西
The vampire hunter is playing this game again
吸血鬼猎人再打了这游戏
You're playing Tremble Isle again
你战栗孤岛再玩一遍
You're replaying Nine Knights
九骑士再玩一遍
You haven't really replayed this game
你这游戏你没有怎么重新玩哈
I've been playing The Elder Scrolls IV: Oblivion Remastered recently
最近一直在玩上古卷轴四重制版
That's the game
那就是这个游戏
If you don't do the side quests
你如果不不打支线的话
If you don't collect them
你都不收集的话
Then what's the point of life?
那还人生还有什么意义呢
Just completing the main storyline?
只是完成主线
Just watching an animation and that's it?
看个动画片就完了吗
Right?
对不对
That would be pretty boring.
那就没有意思了
You need to immerse yourself in the story.
你要体验中这剧情的啊
A plot filled with twists and turns is what makes it interesting.
命运多舛多现实结局它才有意思
So you should definitely take a gap year for yourself.
所以你人生一定要给自己留gap year给自己
No matter what, give your child their own space.
无论是怎么样给你孩子一定空间
He's not doing well in his studies now.
他现在学习不好
Before he was 12, he might not have been good at English.
12岁之前可能英文学不好的时候
He just couldn't get it.
他就学不好了
Parents should allow their children's grades to drop.
鸟要允许孩子成绩下降
They should allow him to take a break from school.
允许他休学
They should allow him to pursue something he loves. Even if it's a person or a celebrity. Or something he's passionate about. In the end, it will fade away. It will fade away But at the age when I was being dramatic My parents gave me this opportunity
允许他为了自己所爱的事情去追求一些东西 哪怕这东西是个人或者是个明星 或者他喜欢的东西 这个东西它最终它会消亡 会消逝 但是我在中二的年纪来讲 父母给了我这种机会
To put my studies on hold
让我放下学业
And pursue what I truly love
能让我追寻自己喜欢的东西
What a wonderful thing
多好的事啊
This is also a kind of luck
这也是一种幸运
In the eyes of others
就在其他人眼里看来
Oh, you didn't get into the Adult Attached High School
哎呀你没上成人大附中
How pitiful
这多可怜
Maybe I was never meant for Renda High School
我也许本身天生就不是人大附中的命
Even if I could get in
我即使能考上来以后
Even if I got into Tsinghua or Peking University
我考上清华北大
Would I be happy?
我会快乐吗
I would find out that among these geniuses
我会发现在这些天才里边
I am just an ordinary person
我只不过是个很平常的人
No matter how hard I try
我再怎么努力
I can't match those with natural talent
也没那些天赋好的人
Or those who work hard
或者那些努力的人
They can work ten or a hundred times harder than I do
人家能努力的程度是我的十倍百倍
So places like that aren't meant for me
所以那种地方就不该我去
I've been to Peking University
我去过北大
I've been to Tsinghua University
去过清华
I've seen my classmates
看我的同学
I've seen my classmates who got into Peking and Tsinghua
看我考上北大清华的同学
Some of my Peking and Tsinghua classmates stayed on as faculty
我北大清华同学有留校的
Some are classmates from Beijing
有的是北京的同学
That's right
没错
staying at Peking and Tsinghua Universities
留在北大清华
they have always been exceptional learners
他们学习从来就是特别好
far more talented than I am
那比我天才都十倍百倍以上的
they belong there
他们就应该待在哪
they should become doctors
他们就应该成为医生
they should become engineers
他们就应该成为工程师
they have such a reputation
他们就有这样的名
they have such qualities
有这样的什么
My cousin is also at Tsinghua. Right? He's a local candidate. And I have another cousin at Tsinghua. He's a candidate from Beijing. It's like that. So, quite a few people in our family have attended Tsinghua. But let me tell you, I'm not saying I have to go there.
我表弟也在清华 对不对 他是地方考生啊 还有一个表弟在清华 他是北京的考生 都是这样 所以我们家其实上清华的好几个人 但是我跟你讲这些东西不是说明我就得去
Nor am I saying I excelled in middle school.
也不是说明我初中学习好
It’s not that you must study well in high school
高中就学习一定好
but rather that you have such an opportunity
而是有这种机会
it may not truly be suitable for you
未必他真正适合你
so you need to explore your own path in life
所以你要探索出自己的人生道路来
If my parents think that only attending Tsinghua University
如果我的父母觉得只有上清华
or Peking University counts as education
北大才是上学的话
or if they see that I have such talent
或者他们看到我有这种才能的话
they would push me to study
他们就逼着我学习
how miserable my life would be
那我的人生得有多痛苦
It might still be the case now.
那说不定现在还是呢
Right?
对不对
Or maybe they've already jumped off a building.
说不定早就跳楼了
There could be all sorts of outcomes.
说不定什么样都有
Because the competition is going to get fiercer.
因为竞争会越来越激烈
You started in middle school,
你最开始是初中
then high school,
然后是高中
then college,
然后是大学
and then grad school, where you still have to compete in the job market.
然后是研究生进了工作一样要竞争啊
Is competition among Chinese people lacking?
中国人的竞争还少吗
Is the effort of Chinese people insignificant?
中国人的努力还小吗
Chinese people have always been accustomed to enduring such hardships.
中国人从来就是吃这些苦的
So from the very beginning, don’t hold back on your efforts.
所以从一开始就不要努力
From the very beginning, don’t embrace UG ideology.
从一开始就不要搞UG主义
From the very beginning, don’t fall into the theater effect.
从一开始就不要走剧场效应
From the very beginning, don’t get caught up in the rat race with others.
从一开始就不要跟别人卷啊
Although I’m also in a competitive space with my videos now, I find my competition very fulfilling. Because I don’t find it difficult to roll this up But most importantly it’s about giving people a space for emotional release whether they have the chance to do what they love
虽然我现在做视频也很卷 但是我卷的很快乐 因为这个东西我卷起来不费劲 但是最重要来讲 就是你要给人家心灵的一个释放的一个空间 他有没有再去干自己喜欢的事情
create videos
做视频
This is the best job I’ve had in my life
现在是我这一辈子干的最好的一个工作
the happiest job
最快乐的一个工作
it helps me deal with my own psychological issues
又能解决自己的心理问题
and allows me to connect with everyone
又能跟大家交流
And at the same time, I can earn money.
然后同时还能赚到钱
The hundreds of episodes I've done.
我做的这几百期
Not a single one was made because someone forced me to.
我没有一期是谁逼着我说让我做没有
Sometimes, I do feel really exhausted when making them.
我有的时候做的时候很很累
Like today, I've been panting all day.
你像我今天我一直大喘气
Today has been really tiring.
就是今天很累
I just drank that yogurt that makes you need to go to the bathroom.
刚才喝了这个那个那个容易拉屎的酸奶
So now my stomach is rumbling like thunder.
所以现在这个胃里边跟打雷一样啊
It's quite amusing.
特别有意思
But it doesn’t make me feel particularly drained.
但是本身来讲它并不让我觉得啊心特别累
I don’t have that feeling.
没有这样的感觉
It makes me feel joyful when I speak and do things.
让我觉得说话做事情很快乐
This is the kind of feeling I need.
这个是我需要的一种感觉
So, right now, I’m in the best state of my life.
所以来讲现在就是我人生中的最好的状态
Why would I complain?
我怎么会抱怨呢
I’m not going to work anyway.
我又不会去上班
Nothing much will change.
又不会怎么样
So now, it has actually led me to the profession that suits me best.
所以现在反而成就了一个我最适合我的专业
But can I do without something in my major?
但我这个专业少一个东西行吗
Could I not have studied computer science back then? Could I have skipped English? Could I have avoided studying directing and acting? Could I have bypassed sociology? Not learning them would have prevented me from becoming who I am today. So I chose this path from the start.
我当初不学计算机行吗 不学英文行吗 不学表导演行吗 不学社会学行吗 不行不学就造成不了今天的我 所以我当初走这条路
It's the culmination of all my decisions.
就是我所有的结果的一个集合
Missing even a single day or a single detour would have been wrong.
少一天少一个弯路都不对
So these things are truly what have shaped me
所以这些东西才是真正铸就了我
So your life actually doesn't take wrong turns
所以你的人生其实不会走弯路
Any detour is the toughest part
任何的弯路最硬
Every climate will ultimately lead to a final outcome
最气候都会是一个最终的一个结局
It's like playing The Elder Scrolls
就像你玩上古卷轴一样
You take a detour
你走了一个弯路
And find a place that's unexpectedly beautiful
看到了一个哈别有洞天的地方
Collect a legendary weapon
收集了一件传奇武器
And it might make the rest of your life easier
有可能你后边的人生都简单了
You might earn a fortune when you're 30.
你有可能因为你30岁赚到一笔横财
Life becomes simpler at 40.
40岁就变得简单了
You might strike it rich at 40.
有可能你40岁发了一笔大财
And later, you might find a wonderful wife.
后来找了一个特别好的老婆
That's how it goes.
都是这样
So how can you easily judge a person's gains and losses?
所以来讲你怎么能轻易判断人的得与失呢
Don't use your small brain to think about life.
不要用你的功力的小脑袋
Be an enlightened parent.
去想这一辈子的事情啊
No matter what,
做一个开明的父母
You should know that the future is unpredictable.
无论怎么样
You don't even know when they will live or die.
你要知道人生的未来的事情
Why worry about the future?
你不知道你连他什么时候活
If my parents hadn't been so open-minded back then,
什么时候死都不知道
They could have cut off my internet fees, Smashed my computer, Or even broken my legs. But they didn't choose any of those options. They continued paying for my internet, Continued upgrading my computer,
你为什么要担心未来的事情 当时我父母如果没有那么开明的话 断掉我的网费 砸掉我的电脑 打断我的双腿都可以 但他们没有选择任何一项
And I went to school as usual.
继续交着网费啊
They acted like nothing was wrong.
继续帮我升级电脑啊
My dad went to work as usual,
然后我该上学了就上学
And so did my mom.
他们就像没事人一样啊
There was no resistance,
我爸该上班上班
No interference.
我妈该上班上班
My grandparents were also around at the time,
没有任何的反抗
And they didn't think there was anything wrong with me staying at home.
没有任何的干涉
They just thought it was nice to see their grandson every day.
我那时候爷爷奶奶也是在身边
Growing up in such a family environment,
我爷爷奶奶也没觉得我在我在这个家里边待着
How could I not feel like I was chosen by destiny?
有什么不对啊
Right?
就觉得天天能看见孙子挺好
How could I not feel happy about my life?
所以你在这么样一种家庭环境下长大
How could I not feel blessed?
我怎么能不觉得我是天选之子
Maybe not before,
对不对
But after comparing my life with many others,
我怎么能不觉得我的人生快乐
My life has definitely been on a roll.
我怎么能不觉得这人生是被祝福的状态
I'm 41 now,
之前也许没有
And I haven't had a single serious injury or fracture.
但之后我跟众多的人比较了一下我的人生
When I go out to play,
我的人生绝对他妈是开挂了
Others get into car accidents and end up with blood all over their faces,
我到41岁了
But I haven't even scratched a hair on my head.
我身上连一块重伤骨折都没有
What else could this be if not being chosen by destiny?
我在出去玩的时候
So this is a warning from heaven,
别人车祸全他妈翻车
Telling you not to do anything too bad in this life,
全他妈满脸是血
Or else heaven won't bless you. That's how it is. Moreover, You should believe that you are destined for greatness. You can achieve great things in this life. So the source of great achievements isn't from setting grand goals,
我他连根毛都没伤到 我 这还不是天选之子是什么 所以这就是上天给你去敲一个警钟啊 让你这辈子不要干太大的坏事啊 否则老天爷就不保佑你了
But from realizing that your life has been quite ordinary after the fact,
是这样
And feeling disappointed about it.
而且来讲的话
That's the journey of an idealist from hope to disappointment.
让你们应该天命昭昭
But if you're not like that,
这一辈子一定能干成很伟大的事情
If you're more like me,
所以很伟大的事情来的源头
I wanted to play games in junior high,
不是因为你立了大志
Chase girls in college,
而你事后发现自己的人生很平淡
Change majors in my senior year,
然后你会觉得失望
And go abroad.
这就是一个理想主义者
Of course, I left in my junior year.
从赚起希望到失望的最终的过程
So what if life fails?
但是如果你不是那样的人
If you fail, just start over.
你就像我一样一个人呢
Right?
我初二的时候我就想玩游戏
But when I start over, I start from the same place.
大二的时候我就想泡妞
I'm not starting a new life somewhere else,
我大四的时候就想换专业
I'm restarting right here.
就想出国啊
Let's try again, shall we?
当然是大三走的
If you fail in junior high,
所以来讲又怎么样呢
Let's try again.
人生失败了又怎样呢
If that doesn't work,
啊失败了就重开
What if you graduate from junior high?
对不对
You can always learn to perform crosstalk.
但我这重开是原地重开
Right?
我并不是重开了一个人
So the path of life is such that,
我是原地重心
When you truly hit rock bottom,
咱们再念一次嘛
A new opportunity appears.
对不对
So never say you're nothing.
初三不行
Always repeat this phrase:
咱再念一次
If it really doesn't work
实在不行
So what if I graduated from junior high? We could also learn to perform crosstalk. Is that right? So, the journey of life, When you really do cut it off A new turning point has emerged. So never say you're not something.
初中毕业又怎样 咱还可以去学说相声 对不对 所以人生这路啊 等你真正断掉的时候呢 它就出现了新的转机了啊 所以永远不要说自己不是什么东西
Always remember to repeat this phrase
永远要重调重复这句话
I am the chosen one
我是天选之子